You know there's that myth that saying
that cooks don't want to cook for their
family and friends and themselves after
they finish work. Chinese food helps to
get rid of that. Oriental, specifically
Chinese food, is the most efficient way
to feed a lot of people quickly.
I'm bringing you here today for a bunch
of reasons. One, this is more convenient
for me today instead of going to the
restaurant just to film. And two, I
wanted to actually show you what making
Chinese dinner for whole ass Chinese
people looks like in a Chinese home
with Chinese ingredients. For those of
us joining us who did not grow up with
Oriental food culture, specifically
broad pan-Chinese, treat this as a
visual summary of what it looks like to
cook quickly at home. For those of us
joining us who are born and raised by
pan-Chinese food culture, just treat
this as watching some guy [__] up dishes
at home. First of all, there are some
basic and fundamental differences in
mentality [music] between pan-Chinese
Oriental food dining and
Eurocentric Western dining. The first
one, and most obvious, is format of
meal. And what I mean by that is thus,
Asians, [music] actually most
non-Eurocentric, non-Western, non-white,
our format of meal is our main starch,
whether it be bean or bread or rice,
surrounded by flavorful lubes that we
use to choke our starch down. In
Eurocentric Western dining, modern
Western dining specifically, it's meat
with backup singers for you on your
plate and you don't touch anybody else's
food and you wait course by course until
everybody's done their thing. No right
or wrong of it, just different. What
that effectively means is that every
home cooked Chinese meal is effectively
a small buffet. That's something you
need to get into your mind. Second of
all, there is no right or wrong way to
make Chinese food because largely at
home, home cookery, a lot of the Chinese
food that you would happen upon day to
day can be pretty cleanly summarized as
adjective verb noun food.
What that means is
adjective, the descriptor of the sort of
flavor profile, roughly speaking. Verb,
the style of cooking you're doing to it.
And then noun, the main thing you're
cooking. And thusly, I have organized
the ingredients for you to think about
next time you try this at home. Because
with just a few ingredients, you can get
pretty much, let's see, 1 2 3 4 5 6
dishes on the table for five people in
under an hour. I guarantee this. It just
requires changing your mentality.
Comment, like, subscribe. Here we have
the universal constant between all foods
in humanity is salt. Next to that, I
have an amalgamation of different animal
fat, fish, lard, chicken fat all in
here. But if you don't like this, you
can definitely use pure lard, which I
like to do, animal fats. Or if you're
really against the usage of animal fats,
you can use any cooking side of your
choice. So, a dry seasoning. I chose
five spice because it has everything I
like in it, but this could be Sichuan
peppercorn. It could be black pepper. It
could be white pepper. It could be
fennel seeds. It could be anything you
like. Cumin. Depends on if you're from
the north, east, south, west of the
country. It's always an amalgamation of
those few spices. It's essentially just
salt and pepper pepper pepper pepper
pepper. It's salt and four different
kinds of pepper, all right? That's off
to the side. Here is what I call the
mayao lu. It is a mixture of all the
seasonings I would reach for anyways
whenever I'm making Asian-centric food.
So, instead of running back and forth
between my pantry and my stove like a
[__] choo-choo train, I'm just going to
grab the things that I need, put them
into a big squeezy bottle, shake them up
to the ratios that I like, and then just
use it as an all-purpose seasoning.
Because if we're perfectly honest, this
is the flavor profile I like, and every
single dish is going to need this. Asian
food is a cheat code. It's just adding
pre-made flavor. We've outsourced the
browning and the flavor, and we're just
applying it to different ingredients we
like. That's what makes it easy. Why do
certain meals in Western and Eurocentric
cooking take so long? It's probably
because you've been browning [__] all
afternoon. Wake up and simply caramelize
your onions." [__] off, I don't have an
hour and a half to caramelize onions for
dinner, right? Outsource your brown.
Make that a hashtag, outsource the
brown. Next to that is your vegetal
flavor profile. This would be your
mirepoix in Western cooking, your onion,
celery, and carrot, or your onion and
shallot and garlic. For us, it's garlic,
ginger, and leek. This is very young
spring garlic that I fermented. I always
have some at home. I always use young
ginger, skinless fresh ginger if I can
get a hold of it. If you're in the West,
you probably can't. It's unfortunate,
but look out for it. And here is my
leek. I'm a northern boy, so I use
These are what we call flavor pro max.
So, this is just the iPhone of flavors.
This is the pro max. These are the apps
you install to customize your phone. So,
if you want to go in the northern or
direction,
if you want to go into hometown, then
you go into fish saucy and
also pickled lemons. If you want to go
into like the riverlands, you want
fermented bean curds. So, these are your
modifiers for if you wanted to taste
more influenced by another region, this
that and the other. If you had to make
an analogy for Western cooking, it would
kind of be like starting with a
mirepoix, and if you added tomato,
rosemary, and thyme, you would go
Mediterranean. If you went cumin,
paprika, and this that and the other,
you would go kind of almost Turkish.
There's modifiers, cultural modifiers,
but the bases are all the same. These we
may or may not use today moment's notice
based on how I feel. So, we're putting
them off to the side for now. And then
down here
is the foods we're eating today. Today,
we're going to have a
noun verb noun, which is young garlic
chives sauteed with scrambled eggs.
Yeah, that's one dish.
Which is a noun verb noun dish, which is
pickled mustard greens sauteed with my
sliced beef. I've bought pre-sliced beef
because it's cheap here. If you can't
get it, then use whatever meat you like.
It doesn't have to be beef. It can be
intestine, it can be insides of animal,
it could be liver, it could be chicken,
it could be pork, it could be anything
you like. I've just gotten this today,
okay? It's my second dish. I have mah
gan bian dou jiao, dry fried broad
beans, and I'm going to make a salad of
cucumber and wood ear mushrooms. Liang
ban mu er guo huang gua. Here's my dried
dong bei wood ear mushrooms, and here is
the cucumber for that, so that's dish
number four. My starches today will come
in the form of bing that we have
leftover from a Mexican video that we
just filmed a little while back. But
this is the exact same as what we now
use for tuan bing in China. It's the
exact same [__] recipe. White wheat
flour plus warm water plus a bit of fat
plus a bit of salt and some baking
powder, rolled flat and fried in a cold
wok. If you don't want to do this, buy
tortillas. They're the exact same. Don't
let anybody culturally gatekeep your
food, yeah? And of course you're going
to make some rice for my southern
colleagues because not everybody here
likes wheat-based food. Generally, in
broad strokes, up north we do
wheat-based, down south they do
rice-based, okay? I am going out of my
way to be all accommodating. This is way
too much already. I'm cooking for 1 2 3
4 5 6 people right now, and we got to
get this done in under an hour. You
believe me?
You don't have to. Like, the trick is it
doesn't matter if you believe me or not,
it's going to happen anyways. It is
right now 4:30. First thing I'm going to
do is wash the rice. So, in a pot, I'm
just going to cook this rice. Now, I
usually use a rice cooker, and I highly
recommend that everybody have one at
home. I am very, very blessed to be
given this lovely little toy that I'll
tell you about in just a second over
there, which is an impulse induction
stove, which means that I can control my
pan temperature at any given point with
a granularity of 1 degree. What that
also means is that theoretically I could
never burn this rice, which is what most
people are afraid of, and I can relegate
all of my cooking to one stove. Now, if
you want to pretend like, "Oh, if you
are Asia, you finger your food and know
how much water." Yeah, you can be an
[__] and say that, but if you want a
ratio for how to cook rice, Uh
effectively just however much rice you
measure out however much water. Wash
your rice and strain it as hard as you
can, and then add that weight and water,
and you have a perfect ratio. And then
more or less water makes a difference of
texture. So, if you want stickier or
squishier rice or not. As a general way
of measuring, you want 150 g of raw rice
to one like full-ass human being. But,
you also have to account for size of
human being.
There you go. So,
my stove I'm very happy to have is
capable of just setting the temperature
to 107. So, I'm just going to put it up
to 107, let that come to a boil, and
then I'm just going to let it cook. So,
I have my rice going. Now, next thing
I'm going to do is boil water for my
mortar, so I can soak it for the salad.
I could do it in cold water if I had
more time, but we're trying to cook
quickly today, so I'm just going to do
it with hot water. Now, this is another
party trick. I can send 10 kW of power
directly into this pan and boil cold
water in under a minute. Of course, if
you don't have this at home, use a
kettle. Same idea.
Cool. All right.
Food DJ,
and water goes in, and we're good to go.
So, that's going to soak and get nice
and plump. We'll run it through cold
water later. All right. Next thing we're
going to do is start seasoning our beef.
So, in here is a lot of different
seasonings. So, we're going to shake
shake shake shake shake. Just season in
the container that this meat came in.
Now, this is where my Western cooking
brain gets the better of me. I'm going
to put in my dry spices to my cold meats
because I don't want my spices to burn
in my rip-roaring hot pan. Now, if
you're kind of squeamish about seasoning
with your hands, feel free to do this
with a spatula or a spoon. Grab a little
bit of fat, run it through the meat.
Beautiful. We have seasoned meat. Put my
greens off to the side cuz they're going
to go into the pan at the same time, and
this is prep done [snorts] for this
dish. All right. Now, here are eggs.
We're going to season with salt
individually cuz I don't want that brown
muddy look my eggs. That's the only
reason I'm seasoning separately with
salt. If I seasoned it with this brown
sauce, which you can do, my mom would
say, "Zang si si da." And she would
refuse to eat it. That's the annoying
part about Asian food sometimes is that
you have so little to complain about
that you're finding literally anything
you can to complain about. All right.
>> [clears throat]
>> Cool.
The prep on this is done as well. This
doesn't actually even need prep. But if
you want just to make your life a little
bit easier, you can grease them
beforehand. I rarely ever do. But you
know what? Since we're already here,
why the hell not?
Put my fat in.
Fat goes on top of the ingredients, so
when we turn over into the pan, fat is
the first thing that hits the pan, and
then I get my aromatics going, and my
dish is done quicker, right? Same with
this. Little bit of fat.
Now, I'm going to pre-season my chive a
little bit. So, as you can see, slowly
we're starting to collapse the prep. The
prep is getting smaller and smaller and
smaller. Another thing is while most of
the time if you were making a Western
meal, you would be thinking about doing
the roasting of the side dish, making
the gravy, making the garnish, making
the this, that, and the other. It's
exactly the same amount of effort spread
into more dishes. There's no better or
worse of it. It's just this is how I
would prefer to eat. I don't want one
dish that doesn't change. I want to have
the choice of eating like every meal as
a small buffet. So, I'd rather spend
that effort spread out across four or
five different dishes. But that is a
preference, okay? So, let's work on the
salad. You want two mil slices. Feel
free to use a mandolin for this if you
so wish. I'm just too lazy at home to
clean up multiple tools. So, I'm just
going to break this down with my
favorite knife.
I'm doing that [__] chef thing again
where while no one's watching, I move
the two [__] ends off to the corner,
so it makes it seem like I have the best
knife skills on Earth.
>> Well, why do you cut it like have an
angle?
>> Because the the cucumber are lying down
on an angle. So, if I angle my knife,
I'll end up with, you know, if not
square and plumb, then at least
trapezoidal strips in cross-section.
But, that's just the nerdiness in me.
You don't need to do that.
So, this, because it's been hot water,
it's already pretty much bloomed out.
You stop blooming this the moment you
like the texture. I like the texture, so
I'm going to strain it out now.
Wood ear mushroom, dried, is one of the
most versatile ways to get good
nutrients and more fiber into your
system and vegetable. And it should be
available wherever Chinese people are
available. And Chinese people are
available everywhere. Don't bother with
trying to shock it in ice. It's not
necessary. Just run it with cold tap
water, and eventually it'll cool down.
What time is it right now?
>> 20 minutes.
>> It's only been 15 minutes?
Amazing. What I usually do at this point
is I put all of my salad ingredients
together. I'm going to do a little bit
of this pickled lemon brine. Not
necessary. I'm going to do a little bit
of fish sauce, cuz I think that goes
really well with everything in here. I'm
going to go in a little bit more with my
shaky shaky flavor. Mm.
Yeah.
Chop up a little bit of bird's eye chili
to go in there. And
and put [clears throat] in a little bit
of black vinegar. Just a bit to season
it and bring it up, make it a little
bright. Once again, now that we're
halfway done, I want to remind you that
you don't have to go this balls out. I'm
cooking for six people while
bullshitting with you with a time
constraint. If you wanted to pair this
down to only like
a few dishes, you absolutely could.
Let's get started, shall we? Grab one of
your favorite woks. Turn on your
extractor. Now, I'm going to start with
my scrambled eggs and garlic chive. My
jiu cai chao ji dan. I'm going to heat
my wok up and first make my scrambled
eggs, cuz that's most important. Feel
free to roll your pan around.
Do not feel the need to cook a
round-bottom wok on a flat burner. This
is just what I do cuz I think it's fun.
Give it some time to set.
Oh, look, our rice is done. Yeah, see?
It's been 20 minutes, our rice is done.
Go in there with a pair of chopsticks
and fluff it up. Yeah, it's even better
than a rice cooker, man. And the best
part about this do see, no burnt bottom.
You have nothing to worry about. Check
the doneness of your rice.
Yeah, that's exactly my favorite
doneness of rice.
Leave it in there, let it steam through,
and your rice is done. Cool, easy. All
right.
In goes my garlic chives. With the fat,
I'm going to add a little bit cuz I was
shy with the fat the first time. And
also, I don't know how you guys feel
about this, but I feel like this is a
better way to put more vegetables in
your system. Cuz every single time we go
overseas for vacation, you have to like
come prepared with all of your medicines
and your fiber and your extras.
You think like, how do people [__] here?
Like, I thought I was a meat eater until
I went over there and was like, "Damn,
man." It goes in. That's one thing off
the board.
Nice and shiny. All right, first dish
done.
That goes on the table.
And another thing I love about cooking
at home is I can do it all in one wok. I
have pot for rice and pot for the rest
of the food.
Grab a bit of my garlic, grab a bit of
my ginger, stir.
You can spend your entire life thinking
there's excuses for why you can't make
tasty food at home, or you can just give
it a try. And yet, someone is already
going to say, "Well, we don't all have a
powerful burner at home." That's true.
So, buy one, or realize that I'm only
using 160° C on my pan right now, which
is perfectly achievable in any burner at
home. And listen to the noise. That's
not a lot of heat. Add a little bit of
water.
Thick brown sauce,
well-cooked beans. Dish number two. I'm
going to give my pan another rinse.
Okay, time for dish number three. In
your ladle goes some oil. And the first
thing we're going to do is get the
mustard greens in to get rid of some of
the acidity. But
my ginger, my garlic, scallions, little
bit of five spice into my veggies.
Once everything is half cooked but still
kind of half raw, in goes my meat, my
protein. And you just start mixing and
frying, mixing and frying. Now, if you
want this to taste better, what you do
at this point is add a lot,
a lot, a lot of fat. But we're trying to
all be a little bit healthier here at
the company, so I'm going to try to stay
away from too much fat in the cooking.
Now, the western-minded cooks in you
will be thinking about, "Oh, why didn't
you sear your meat? you brown it off?"
We're not making a steak. And you know,
if you look into my wok, that's pretty
brown, man. If I'm giving it via soy, in
broad strokes, it's in the same
neighborhood as if I were to be giving
it with searing my steak off. It's a
different style of cooking, right?
>> [cough]
>> No right or wrong with it. Just I've
already outsourced my browning to the
bottles.
>> [clears throat]
>> So, I'm not going to waste money on a
weeknight searing everything off.
Now, if you cannot help yourself and
must garnish, please feel free to
sprinkle the top of this with cilantro
and scallions. But it's not necessary.
These tortillas can go in the microwave
for a quick reheat.
All right.
Oops.
Sorry, I [__] that up a little bit. I
had some old green onions. How are we
doing for time?
So, I have rice, stack of starch. I have
a salad. I have three hot dishes. If you
really wanted to bulk it out, what you
could do is make a Chinese charcuterie
board, which is actually a thing. So,
where I'm from, the tradition is to
always have a plate of cured sausage and
meat on the table to have with dinner.
>> Okay.
>> You heard dinner was ready?
[__] [__] That is how I put
dinner on the table. What time is it
right now?
We started when? 4:30. Perfect. So, 45
minutes plus bullshitting. Without any
talking, that could have been half an
hour. And that's enough dinner for five
to six people. Talk often, talk soon.
Take care. I'm sorry for coming like
subscribe. I'm sorry for the no [__]
this episode. I just wanted to show you
how dinner is made at home. Sorry if I
wasn't as talkative. Hope this has been
informative and indeed useful. Talk
often, talk soon. Comment, like,
subscribe. Take care. Bye-bye, guys.